YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 5. International Work
Sophia Smith Collection
The microfilmed records of the International Division are far more extensive than those that have survived in their original format, relating to subjects that are barely touched upon in the hard copy files, such as budgets, or not addressed at all, such as activities related to specific countries like Australia, Canada, and a number of European countries.
Minutes and Reports of the Foreign Division also include minutes and reports of "Sections," such as those for Europe and Latin America. There are also other records such as newsletters to the staff abroad and the International studies for the various countries. For minutes related to international work after 1961, see the Original Format records.
The Subject File includes some administrative records concerning finances, annual meetings, committees, statistics, relationship with the World YWCA, subjects like emigration/immigration and "World Emergency" (World War II); and files of publications, lists, manuals and other miscellaneous activities of the International Division. The bulk of the records are extensive reports, correspondence and other materials arranged alphabetically by country. The international work department is notable for retaining far more correspondence than other departments of the National Association, perhaps because it was often the best documentation of the department's activities and accomplishments abroad and thus had a secondary usefulness for promoting international work in the local associations. The voluminous reports and correspondence of overseas secretaries are the heart of this portion of the microfilm, but there is also material about conferences, conventions, history, studies, real estate, personnel; and constitutions and publications from national programs, in China for example. [Note that reels 152-153, containing reports from China, are missing. The Original Format Records appear to include at least a few of these missing reports.]
Records relating to International Work can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Foreign Division
Subject Files
Foreign
Foreign Countries
International
Original Format Records, 1907-2000, n.d., 13 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
Most of the original format records of international work, with the exception of Minutes, some staff reports, and the International Study, where there is a great deal of overlap, were discarded after microfilming, so it is crucial to consult the microfilm.
The bulk of the surviving paper records are dated from the 1920s through the 1980s. There is a great deal of duplication of records on the microfilm, but they also include materials donated to the National Board Archives after the microfilming was completed that probably were not filmed, such as office files of individuals working on a particular project or program.
1970-2000 (post-microfilm) materials include published and printed materials about the international program of the YWCA, minutes (far more sparse than for earlier decades), records of numerous committees active in that period, and a large proportion of the Projects and Programs Series, reflecting the shift after World War II from focus on recruiting, training and supporting overseas secretaries to broader subject programs. Countries and Regions is a combination of older records, such as staff reports and minutes of various Sections that are duplicated on the microfilm; and reference materials about the various countries and regions that were collected by the National Board Library/Archives from various sources, including individual YWCA personnel.
See also Related Materials.
The Original Format Records are arranged in six series as follows:
I. GENERAL, HISTORY, AND ADMINISTRATION
II. MINUTES AND REPORTS
III. COMMITTEES
IV. PROJECTS AND PROGRAMS
V. PUBLICATIONS
VI. REGIONS AND COUNTRIES
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey); Asia--Description and travel--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; China--History--1912-1949--Sources; International education--History--Sources; International relations--History--20th century--Sources; East Asia--Description and travel--Sources; Moore, Elisabeth Luce; Women in development--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Young Women's Christian Associations--India--History; Young Women's Christian Associations--Latin America--History; Young Women's Christian Associations--Turkey
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
Because the YWCA of the U.S.A. was a participant in an international movement and affiliated with the World YWCA, information related to international work/relations is located throughout the records. The following materials are particularly relevant:
RECORD GROUP 1. SERIES VI. and VII contain reference files on 'Foreign' YWCAs and the World YWCA.
Records of early international work by American YWCAs can be found in the records of the predecessor organization known as the American Committee in RECORD GROUP 2.
YWCA of the U.S.A. officer and staff correspondence with YWCAs worldwide and with the World YWCA is in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE.
Discussions of the program for International Work can be found in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES.
Public advocacy on international problems is documented in the work of the Public Affairs program in SERIES III of RECORD GROUP 6.
Tools and methods for presenting the concept of World Fellowship and the international work of the YWCA to various Constituent Groups can be found in SERIES IV and SERIES V of RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
SERIES 6. PUBLICATIONS: The main YWCA serial Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine/YWCA Interchange has many articles on international work and YWCAs in other countries.
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS contains a large collection of photographs of YWCAs in other countries.
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS contains audio for a 1982 slide presentation, "Breaking Barriers;" video from the Uganda Study-Travel Program and a "Fact Finding" trip to El Salvador in 1991; and 1991-92 visits between Chinese and U.S. YWCA leaders.
Elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection
The Records of the Committee of Correspondence contain correspondence with YWCA women.
The Sophia Smith Collection also houses the papers of a number of YWCA Overseas and World YWCA staff members including:
Bessie Boies Cotton
Elizabeth Dickerson Papers
Eldri Dieson Papers
Frances Drake
Polly Babcock Feustal
Virginia Heim George
Ruth Lois Hill
Garnet J. Knights
Ina Ruth Hillis Lackey
Elmina Rose Lucke
Elisabeth Luce Moore
Eleanora Davis Pim
Frances Ticknor
Ruth Van Meter
Ruth Frances Woodsmall
The SSC Periodicals collection contains Today: Magazine of the YWCA of India for 1963-79
See also the online exhibit of five YWCA overseas secretaties (Bessie Boies Cotton, Virginia Heim George, Ruth Lois Hill, Elmina R. Lucke, and Ruth Frances Woodsmall) "An Ever-Widening Circle of Friendship": YWCA Overseas Secretaries from China to Liberia.
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. GENERAL, HISTORY, AND ADMINISTRATION 1907-97, n.d.
  This series contains published and unpublished historical and general articles about the international work of the YWCA; general administrative records regarding the overall purpose and mission of the YWCA's international work; personnel lists, job descriptions, and biographical files; and annual reports from the years through 1913, and 1971-72. There are fragmentary files concerning conferences and events, and general correspondence.
- SERIES II. MINUTES AND REPORTS, 1907-93
  There is a fairly complete run of minutes and reports documenting international work of the from the Foreign Department/Division through the World Relations Committee in the 1980s and early 1990s in this series. From 1907-61, these records are duplicated by the microfilm; International Division/World Relations Committee minutes from 1961-93 were not microfilmed. Additional minutes for individual committees, e.g., Finance, are in Series III.
- SERIES III. COMMITTEES 1908-22, 1946-93, n.d.
  This series primarily contains minutes for committees engaged in international work, but there is a variety of additional documentation, including reports, correspondence, printed material, financial files, rosters, and directories. The committee activities documented here are heavily concentrated from the 1950s through the 1980s; only committees devoted to finance were active earlier.
- SERIES IV. PROJECTS AND PROGRAMS, 1910-2000, n.d.
  A wide variety of subjects encompassing the many components of the YWCA's international work are covered in this series, from World Mutual Service (or World Fellowship) beginning in 1910 to Education for Global Responsibility in the 1990s. The bulk of these records date from the 1970s on and include brochures, publications and other printed materials; proposals; reports; correspondence, minutes, and resource kits. It appears that some of these records consist of office files that were donated to the Library/Archives by individual staff members who worked on a particular program or project.
- SERIES V. PUBLICATIONS, 1907-98, n.d.
  The Foreign Department/Division of the National Association produced some of it's own brochures, flyers, pamphlets, charts, maps, and newsletters, and they make up the bulk of this series. Publications about specific committees, projects, or programs are located in Series III. and IV., and those specific to a particular country or region are located in Series VI. Publications by others about international work are in Series I.
- SERIES VI. REGIONS AND COUNTRIES, 1906-95
  This series is a combination of older records, such as staff reports and minutes of various Sections that are duplicated on the microfilm; and reference materials about the various countries and regions that were collected by the Library/Archives from various sources, including individual YWCA personnel. General records consist of scrapbooks that appear to have been maintained by staff members over the years; records and publications of the International Survey of the YMCA and YWCA, carried out in the late 1920s and early 1930s; and minutes of the Section Chairmen. The scrapbooks were not microfilmed, but the Survey records and Section Chairmen minutes were. Files on individual countries and regions vary from those that are one folder containing a handful of publications (Argentina) to others like China, Japan, and Latin America, that consist of more than a document box of studies, minutes, reports, and publications, the bulk of which has been microfilmed. Besides the above mentioned types of material, the country files include correspondence, speeches, histories, publicity files, statements of purpose and policy, printed materials, and legal documents.
- SERIES I. HISTORY, GENERAL, AND ADMINISTRATION
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - History
    - World Cooperation of the Young Women's Christian Associations of the United States of America: A Record of the Foreign Work of the American Associations, 1866-1929 comp. by Elizabeth Wilson, n.d. (Box 305, Folder 1)
    - World Cooperation of the Young Women's Christian Associations of the United States of America: A Record of the Foreign Work of the American Associations,1930-1935 comp. by Margaret E. Burton, n.d. (Box 305, Folder 2)
    - The Connection of the Foreign Division of the Young Women's Christian Association with Governments by Sarah S. Lyon (M. A. thesis, Columbia University), 1932 (Box 305, Folder 3)
    - "'At Home Abroad': A Summary History of the Foreign Program of the YWCA of the United States," 1960 (Box 305, Folder 4)
    - "A Comparative Study of Six YWCAs: Lebanon, South Africa, Norway, Taiwan, Greece, United States" by Mary Beth Eklund, circa 1975-76 (Box 305, Folder 5)
  - Articles about the YWCA's international program by others
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-1974, n.d. (Box 305, Folder 6)
    - "YWCA: International Success Story," National Geographic, Dec 1963; and scrapbook of public response letters, 1963-64 (Box 305, Folder 7)
  - Organization and functions
    - Foreign Department/Division
      - Statements, reports, convention resolutions, minutes, and memoranda, 1908-58 (Box 305, Folder 8)
      - "Manual for Foreign Field Staff," 1956 (Box 305, Folder 9)
    - International Division
      - "Meeting on Future Structure of the International Division Committee and Staff," 1964 (Box 305, Folder 10)
      - Charter, 1970 (Box 305, Folder 11)
    - World Relations/Global Affairs Unit: correspondence, memoranda, reports, and statements, 1977-96, n.d. (Box 305, Folder 12)
  - Position papers and statements, 1978-87 (Box 305, Folder 13)
  - Personnel
    - Chairman/Director/Executive and miscellaneous World Relations Unit positions: job descriptions, 1964-83 (Box 305, Folder 14)
    - International Division/World Relations Unit committees and subcommittees: rosters, 1960-79 (Box 305, Folder 15)
    - Overseas secretaries
      - Rosters, [see also XF Committee for its earlier directories of former overseas secretaries]
        - 1959, 1981-85 (Box 306, Folder 1)
        - "Living Foreign Staff Lists," 1982, 1988-89 (Box 306, Folder 2)
      - Biographical files, A-Z, 1909-88
        - A-R (Box 306, Folder 3-21)
        - Smith-Z (Box 307, Folder 1-5)
  - Annual reports
    - 1907-13 (Box 307, Folder 6-7)
    - 1970: Botswana; Ceylon; Columbia; Fiji; Iran; Kenya; Liberia; Pakistan; Philippines; Rhodesia; South Africa; Taipei, Taiwan; Tanzania; Thailand; Turkey; Uganda; and Zambia (Box 307, Folder 8)
    - 1971: Ethiopia; Kenya; Liberia; Philippines; Rhodesia; South Africa; Taipei, Taiwan; Tanzania; Thailand; Turkey; Uganda; and Zambia (Box 307, Folder 9)
  - Conferences
    - 5th and 6th: programs, 1918-19 (Box 307, Folder 10)
    - International Study Conference on World Reconstruction, 1948: report, 1949, [see also Programs and projects - Reconstruction work] (Box 307, Folder 11)
    - All-Africa YWCA Conference, 1960; International Development, 1992 (Box 307, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence, 1957, 1976-97 (Box 307, Folder 13)
  - Events: programs, calendars, itineraries, and articles, 1980-81, 1993-94, 1997 (Box 307, Folder 14)
  - Memorabilia: guest book, 1962-81 (Box 307, Folder 15)
- SERIES II. MINUTES AND REPORTS
  - Foreign Division
    - 1907-17 (Box 308, Folder 1-20)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 308A, Folder 1-6)
  - Foreign and Overseas Department, 1921 (Box 308A, Folder 7-8)
  - Foreign Division
    - 1922-39 (Box 308A, Folder 9-23)
    - 1940-59 (Box 309, Folder 1-24)
    - 1960-Feb 1961 (Box 310, Folder 1)
  - International Division, Mar 1961-71 (Box 310, Folder 2-11)
  - World Relations Steering Committee, 1979-84 (Box 310, Folder 12)
  - World Relations Committee, 1985-93 (Box 310, Folder 13-14)
- SERIES III. COMMITTEES
  - Cooperation for Development Core (World Relations): minutes, 1980-84 (Box 311, Folder 1)
  - Finance
    - Finance and Personnel (Foreign Division): minutes, 1921-22 (Box 311, Folder 2)
    - Special Committee on Nationwide Foreign Finance/Foreign Finance Campaign (Foreign Division): minutes, 1914-15; reports, 1908-09 (Box 311, Folder 3)
  - International Building Fund (International Division and World Relations Unit)
    - Brochures, (circa 1976) (Box 311, Folder 4)
    - Ad Hoc Building Fund
      - Building Fund Project Proposal, 1960-64 (Box 311, Folder 5)
      - Procedures, polices, and taxes; lists and clearances; status of fund; correspondence; and minutes and final documents, 1961-66 (Box 311, Folder 6)
    - Minutes
      - 1966-73 (Box 311, Folder 7-8)
      - 1976-77, 1987 (Box 311, Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1966-88 (Box 311, Folder 10)
    - Personnel, 1966-82 (Box 311, Folder 11)
    - Policies, 1964-73 (Box 311, Folder 12)
    - Special Accounts, 1965-93 (Box 311, Folder 13)
  - International Leadership Exchange and Development Task Force (ILEAD) (formerly ILEAD Committee), 1987-91 (Box 311, Folder 14)
  - Leadership Development (International Relations and World Relations Unit): minutes,1954-84 (Box 312, Folder 1-8)
  - Projects/Projects and Budgets/Projects and Grants (International Division and World Relations Unit): agendas and minutes, 1960-79 (Box 312, Folder 9-12)
  - World Issues (World Relations Unit): minutes
    - Subcommittee, 1980-82 (Box 313, Folder 1)
    - Core, 1983-84 (Box 313, Folder 2)
  - XF (Ex Foreign Secretaries)
    - Rosters/directories of Committee members, (1946?)-81 (Box 313, Folder 3-4)
    - Minutes, 1961-77 (Box 313, Folder 5-6)
    - Reports
      - Triennial, 1961, 1964 (Box 313, Folder 7)
      - Treasurer, 1956-77 (Box 313, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1958-84 (Box 313, Folder 9-10)
    - Membership, 1961-77 (Box 313, Folder 11)
    - Projects
      - Miscellaneous, 1958-68 (Box 313, Folder 12)
      - Bessie Cotton Memorial Fund, 1957-63 (Box 313, Folder 13)
      - Book (Emissaries: The Overseas Work of the American YWCA, 1895-1970 by Nancy Boyd), 1980-86 (Box 313, Folder 14)
    - Publications
      - Article from The YWCA Magazine, 1963 (Box 313, Folder 15)
      - XF News From Everywhere (newsletter), 1955-82 (Box 313, Folder 16-17)
- SERIES IV. PROJECTS AND PROGRAMS
  - Education for Global Responsibility
    - General, 1993-97 (Box 314, Folder 1)
    - Barbados trip, 1994-96 (Box 314, Folder 2)
    - Jamaica trip, 1994 (Box 314, Folder 3)
    - Kenya trip, 1995-96 (Box 314, Folder 4)
  - End War - Build Peace Task Force, 1971-73, [see also Peace Network] (Box 314, Folder 5)
  - Health and physical education, circa 1923 (Box 314, Folder 6)
  - Human Rights Heroes Campaign, 1997-98 (Box 314, Folder 7)
  - International Laboratory on Developing Youth Leadership and Program: proposal, 1977 (Box 314, Folder 8)
  - International Study Program
    - General, 1967, 1977-79, 1983, 1989 (Box 314, Folder 9)
    - South Africa Study Program, 1982-86 (Box 314, Folder 10)
    - Uganda, 1990-92 (Box 314, Folder 11)
  - International Training Institutes
    - 1940-63 (Box 314, Folder 12)
    - 1965-(67?) (Box 314, Folder 13)
    - 1969-(70?), n.d. (Box 314, Folder 14)
  - International Voluntary Service: brochure and reports from volunteers, 1965-77 (Box 315, Folder 1)
  - International Women's Day: brochures, 1998; and kit, 2000 (Box 315, Folder 2)
  - LA [Latin America]/USA Exchange Project, 1961 (Box 315, Folder 3)
  - Lily K. Haass Memorial Fund (file of Lydia Johnson), 1964-67 (Box 315, Folder 4)
  - Middle-East Encounter meetings, 1982-86
    - Ad Hoc Planning Group, 8 Jan 1983 (Box 315, Folder 5)
    - 4 & 5 Mar 1983 (Box 315, Folder 6)
    - 8 Apr 1983 (Box 315, Folder 7)
    - (Bayard Rustin)14 Apr 1983 (Box 315, Folder 8)
    - 19 May 1983-12 Sep 1983 (Box 315, Folder 9-11)
    - World Council Meeting, Nov 1983 (Betty Jo Swayze) (Box 315, Folder 12)
    - 12 Dec 1983-2 Apr 1986 (Box 315, Folder 13-19)
    - A Middle East Encounter: In Search of Peace and Justice-A YWCA Study Action Model (1983) and 1988(revision) (Box 315, Folder 20)
  - National Forum on Women, 1973-80 (Box 315, Folder 21)
  - Nestle boycott
    - YWCA
      - Correspondence, 1979-82, 1984 (Box 315, Folder 22-23)
      - Publications: Implementing the Nestle Resolution: A Program Paper (1980) and miscellaneous (Box 316, Folder 1)
      - Cleveland YWCA: correspondence, printed material, and position statement, 1978-81 (Box 316, Folder 2)
    - Boycott action: flyers, petitions, songs, and stickers, 1978-83, n.d. (Box 316, Folder 3)
    - International Boycott Committee: minutes, 1980-82 (Box 316, Folder 4)
    - Nestle Infant Formula Audit Commission
      - Charter, Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws and Procedures (n.d.), and report by The Nestle Coordination Center for Nutrition (1982) (Box 316, Folder 5)
      - Press conferences (Muskie and others): transcripts, 1982-83 (Box 316, Folder 6)
      - Quarterly reports, 1982-84 (Box 316, Folder 7-9)
      - Personnel: mailing list, congressional committees, organizations, and biography of Edmund S. Muskie, 1980, n.d. (Box 316, Folder 10)
    - Publications by others
      - INFACT Newsletter, 1979-83 (Box 316, Folder 11)
      - INFACT Update
        - 1979-80 (Box 316, Folder 12)
        - 1981-84 (Box 317, Folder 1)
      - Nestle News (press releases), 1979-84 (Box 317, Folder 2)
      - UNICEF and WHO, 1978-82 (Box 317, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1977-84, n.d. (Box 317, Folder 4-5)
    - Final agreement: press releases, publications, memoranda, and reports, 1984 (Box 317, Folder 6)
  - Partners in Development Task Force: Kenya, 1997-98 (Box 317, Folder 7)
  - Peace Network (Jimmie Woodward), 1971-72, [see also End War - Build Peace Task Force] (Box 317, Folder 8)
  - Peace with Justice Task Force, 1975 (Box 317, Folder 9)
  - Reconstruction work, 1946-47, [see also Conferences - International Study Conference on Women in World Reconstruction] (Box 317, Folder 10)
  - United Nations
    - UNICEF, 1981-82, 1990 (Box 317, Folder 11)
    - International Women's Year,1974-75, 1977, n.d. (Box 317, Folder 12)
    - World Conference of the United Nations Decade for Women 1980 (Box 317)
    - U.S. regional meetings and State Department briefings (Rosalie Oakes, Jewel Graham, and Roshan Billimoria, 1979-1980, n.d. (Box 318, Folder 1-3)
    - Project proposal for follow-up community outreach program, Apr 1980 (Box 318, Folder 4)
    - Women's Mid-Decade Dialogue
      - General (Roshan Billimoria), 1980-81, n.d. (Box 318, Folder 5)
      - Translating Global Concern into Local CommunityPrograms: Women's Mid-Decade Dialogue (1983) (Box 318, Folder 6)
  - Washington Cathedral window
    - Dedication, 1977-82 (Box 318, Folder 7)
    - Donor lists, 1973 (Box 318, Folder 8)
    - Printed material about, 1977-78, 1994 (Box 318, Folder 9)
    - Progress reports, 1974-76 (Box 318, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller, Mary: correspondence, 1973 (Box 318, Folder 11)
    - Sayre, Elizabeth: correspondence, memoranda, and meeting minutes, 1973-75 (Box 318, Folder 12-13)
    - Services, 1944-76, 1994 (Box 319, Folder 1)
  - World Mutual Service (World Fellowship)